<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maurício Vancine</title>
    <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mauriciovancine.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Maurício Vancine</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Maurício Vancine, 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Maurício Vancine</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Host diversity outperforms climate as a global driver of symbiont diversity in the bird‐feather mite system</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-gusmao-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-gusmao-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental niche and functional role similarity between invasive and native palms in the Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-bello-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-bello-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We R Live</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/video/2020-05-05-werlive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/video/2020-05-05-werlive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;live-1-por-onde-começar&#34;&gt;Live 1: Por onde começaR?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://werlive.netlify.app/werlive01/werlive01&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/geocastbrasil/liver/-/tree/master/static/werlive01&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZORFVdwtJ1U&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;live-2-por-onde-começar&#34;&gt;Live 2: Por onde começaR?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://mauriciovancine.github.io/werlive/werlive_01/werlive_01&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/geocastbrasil/liver/-/tree/master/static/werlive01&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Material&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eHht0n3Ppcg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Species Distribution Models: an overview</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/2020_talk_sdm_gggc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/2020_talk_sdm_gggc/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Species Distribution Models (SDM) relate species occurrence data with their environmental conditions to estimate the species’ niche and thus predict new areas of possible distribution. In this lecture, I spoke of the main concepts, input data and applications of this approach in the area of Ecology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of landscape modification on species richness patterns of fruit-feeding butterflies in Brazilian Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-santos-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-santos-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fragmented tropical forests lose mutualistic plant-animal interactions</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-marjakangas-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2020-marjakangas-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Landscape metrics in R</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/video/2019-11-27-metricas-paisagem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/video/2019-11-27-metricas-paisagem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this video, at the invitation of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/FelipeSMBarros&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Felipe Sodré&lt;/a&gt;, from the channel &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCLAeX4dyujMoy4xqHvxSDpQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GeoCast Brasil&lt;/a&gt;, I did a rather long live , where I talked about Landscape Ecology and some of the main concepts linked to this discipline, and a practical part about the calculation of landscape metrics using the R language, more specifically using the [&lt;em&gt;landscapemetrics&lt;/em&gt;](https: // r- spatialecology.github.io/landscapemetrics/) package. The presentation and codes can be accessed in this &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/geocastbrasil/landscapemetrics&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;GitLab repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RCTrLx_33D8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introdução à linguagem R: manipulação e visualização de dados</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/workshop/2019_workshop_r_unesp_ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/workshop/2019_workshop_r_unesp_ecology/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A linguagem R vem se destacando nos últimos anos (desde de 2000), como a principal ferramenta para manejo, visualização e análise de dados, principalmente na área de Ecologia, Psicologia, Economia, e mais recentemente, na Ciência de Dados. Neste curso serão abordados quatro temas introdutórios dessa linguagem: (i) introdução e funcionamento da linguagem R e do software RStudio, (ii) estrutura e manipulação de dados, (iii) introdução ao tidyverse, e (iv) visualização de dados. A carga horária será de aproximadamente 08 horas, onde será focada a parte teórico-prática, intercalada com a realização de exercícios para fixação do conteúdo. Ao final do curso, espera-se que os participantes tenham uma noção geral do funcionamento da linguagem e das potenciais aplicações dentro da área de análise de dados ecológicos&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introdução à modelagem de distribuição de espécies usando a linguagem R: teoria e prática</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/workshop/2019_workshop_sdm_cbh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2019 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/workshop/2019_workshop_sdm_cbh/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A ampla disponibilidade de dados sobre a biodiversidade e variáveis ambientais, tem permitido a utilização de diversas análises biogeográficas e macroecológicas, dentre elas, os modelos de distribuição de espécies (MDE). Esse minicurso tem como intuito oferecer uma introdução teórica e prática à técnica de MDE, utilizando a linguagem R. Primeiramente serão apresentados os principais conceitos da teoria de nicho ecológico (Grinnell, Elton e Hutchinson) e da teoria de modelos (espaço geográfico (G), espaço ambiental (E) e diagrama Biótico-Abiótico-Movimentação (BAM)). Seguida à parte teórica, serão apresentados as principais bases de dados (ocorrências e variáveis ambientais), tipos de algoritmos (presença e ausência – GLM, GAM e Random Forest, apenas presença – BIOCLIM, Mahalanobis e Gower, e presença e background – Maxent e SVM), avaliação dos modelos (ROC, AUC e TSS), limites de corte (thresholds) e algumas abordagens de consenso de modelos (ensembles). A parte prática será focada na construção dos modelos através da linguagem R. Inicialmente será feito uma introdução à programação e manejo de dados espaciais na linguagem R, utilizando os pacotes raster e rgdal. Em seguida, será apresentado como obter dados de ocorrências e variáveis ambientais, através dos pacotes spooc e dismo. Uma vez adquiridos os dados, serão feitas análises preliminares dos mesmos, como seleção de ocorrências (um ponto por célula) e de variáveis (correlação, PCA, análise fatorial e VIF). Por fim, serão construídos modelos utilizando os algoritmos mencionados acima, além do cálculo das métricas de avaliação dos mesmos, utilizando os pacotes dismo, randomForest e kernlab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the potential hybridization zones between native and invasive marmosets within Neotropical biodiversity hotspots</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2019-moraes-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2019-moraes-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Land-use changes and the expansion of biofuel crops threaten the giant anteater in southeastern Brazil</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2019-bertassoni-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2019-bertassoni-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial prediction of risk areas for vector transmission of Trypanosoma cruzi in the State of Paraná, southern Brazil</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-ferro-e-silva-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-ferro-e-silva-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATLANTIC AMPHIBIANS: Atlantic Forest Amphibian Communities Dataset</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/2018_talk_data_paper_anfibios_anfoco/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/talk/2018_talk_data_paper_anfibios_anfoco/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Uncertainties about the diversity and distribution of species is one of the main challenges for conservation biology. The Atlantic Forest Biome is considered one of the most threatened biodiversity hotspots in the world, still holding a high number of amphibian species. In this work, we present a detailed compilation of amphibian communities for the Atlantic Forest. The data set was organized based on a wide geographical delimitation of the biome, encompassing ecotones and areas of Paraguay and Argentina. All community information was obtained from articles, books and unpublished literature (graduation monographs, dissertations and theses). We organize information about: 1) sampled habitat, 2) sampling methods, 3) sampling schedule, 4) sampling effort (initial and final month and year), 5) species composition or abundance, 6) endemism, and 7) location geographic (latitude, longitude, country, state, municipality and specific location). We made taxonomic updates based on data from the Amphibian Species of the World: an Online Reference database, for September 2017. The database was structured from 389 references, sampled between 1940 and 2017, which included 1,163 study, for which there are 17,619 records of 528 species with taxonomic certainty. Of the total records, 14,450 (82%) were classified according to the criterion of endemism to the Atlantic Forest Biome, of which 7,787 (44%) were considered endemic. The most representative methods were: 1) visual or auditory search (82.1%), 2) reproductive site search (20%), 3) trap and fall trap (pitfall, 15.3%), and 4) encounter occasional (14.5%). Among the sampled habitats, none was predominant, although the forest habitat was reported more frequently (40.7%). Most of the study sites had sampling carried out in bodies of water: stream within the forest (33.5%), permanent puddle (30.2%), lake (28.9%), marsh (28.6%) %), temporary pool (27.5%), semi-permanent pool (5.8%) and open water stream (4.5%). Species richness was 15.2 ± 11.3 SD, ranging from 1 to 80 species per location. There was a large sampling bias, with the majority of sampling carried out in the states of São Paulo (38.4%), Paraná (14.2%) and Minas Gerais (10.1%), collectively representing almost 63% of researches. This high bias for these three states may have been due to several reasons: 1) description of two or more study sites for the same reference; 2) historical process of training researchers, in addition to encouraging amphibian sampling research by the BIOTA-FAPESP Program; and 3) numerous herpetological collections, which possibly attracted researchers to carry out taxonomic works. The result of this data compilation generated an overview of the diversity, composition, methods and sampling effort of amphibian communities for the Atlantic Forest Biome, representing a huge effort to fill a knowledge gap about amphibian biodiversity in the Neotropical Region. We hope that these data can be used as a tool for the conservation of this group, in addition to being an important data source for studies of macroecological and biogeographic patterns&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ATLANTIC AMPHIBIANS: a data set of amphibian communities from the Atlantic Forests of South America</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-vancine-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-vancine-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Note on the Territorial Limits of the Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-muylaert-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-muylaert-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Landscape Modifications and Climate Changes on the Persistence of Amphibians in the Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/project/fapesp_2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/project/fapesp_2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lack of knowledge about the diversity and distribution of species is one of the main challenges for conservation. Allied to this fact, the  processes resulting from the modifications of the landscape and climate  changes are among the main causes of the loss of world biodiversity,  further aggravating the unfamiliar scenario. Amphibians are among the  vertebrate groups most sensitive to these changes, mainly due to their  particular morphological and ecological characteristics. The Atlantic  Forest Biome still has a high diversity of amphibians and is considered  one of the most threatened biodiversity &lt;em&gt;hotspots&lt;/em&gt; in the world.  Therefore, in this project we will seek: (1) to present an assessment of the surveys of the amphibian communities for the Atlantic Forest, their composition and distribution; (2) to investigate how habitat loss and  fragmentation on the regional scale can affect the current persistence  of amphibians from different reproductive guilds; and (3) to investigate how climate change may affect the future persistence of amphibians of  the genus &lt;em&gt;Brachycephalus&lt;/em&gt;, considered highly sensitive to these climatic  changes. To carry out this project will be used descriptive and spatial  analyzes of the surveys of amphibian communities and Ecological Niche  Models to find suitable areas for the species. We hope to find an  overview of the diversity of amphibian communities and sampling gaps  along the Atlantic Forest. In addition, we expect species with aquatic  reproductive modes to be more affected by the effects of fragmentation  than species with direct development, which will be more affected by  habitat loss. Finally, we expect that the areas currently suitable for  the occurrence of species of the genus &lt;em&gt;Brachycephalus&lt;/em&gt; will suffer a  drastic decrease in the future and will be located in higher altitudes&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency of protected areas in Amazon and Atlantic Forest conservation: A spatio-temporal view</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-sobral-souza-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2018-sobral-souza-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forest cover influences occurrence of mammalian carnivores within Brazilian Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-regolin-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-regolin-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of mining activities on the potential geographic distribution of eastern Brazil mountaintop endemic species</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-pena-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-pena-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High mammal species turnover in forest patches immersed in biofuel plantations</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-beca-etal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/publication/2017-beca-etal/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effect of fragmentation on the persistence of anuran amphibians within the Atlantic Forest</title>
      <link>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/project/fapesp_2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mauriciovancine.github.io/project/fapesp_2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Amphibians are sensitive to habitat loss, fragmentation and habitat quality, particularly because their limited mobility over large distances and high dependence of microhabitats for reproduction. The Atlantic Rainforest has about 400 species of amphibians, and 60 to 85% of them are endemic. Nowadays the Atlantic Rainforest is reduced to 11.4% - 16.0% of its original cover, with 80% of fragments &amp;lt; 50 ha, isolated and poorly connected. Therefore, understanding how the process of fragmentation influences the persistence of amphibians within the Atlantic Rainforest is essential for the development of strategic planning for species conservation. This study will evaluate the effect of landscape structure, relief and levels of urbanization at the regional scale on the persistence of species &lt;em&gt;Vitreorana eurygnatha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vitreorana uranoscopa&lt;/em&gt;. These two species are forest-dependent and have aquatic breeding, therefore are extremely susceptible to fragmentation. To carry out the study, the following steps will be taken: (i) model the potential distribution based on the environmental suitability of the species of interest, (ii) identify landscapes with high environmental suitability and surveys with high sampling effort in order to characterize the regional anurofauna, (iii) evaluate the relative contribution of landscape indices (percentage of forest cover, connectivity, relief and urban proximity) to the persistence of species using model selection for multiple competing hypotheses based on Akaike information theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
